Register of the Alexander Liosnoff papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Okinawa Files (U.S. Civil Administration of the Ryukyu Islands), 1950-2001
  - Printed Materials
    - Okinawa, Keystone of the Pacific, circa 1960s
    - Home Safety Manual, Ryukyus command headquarters, circa 1960s
      In English and Japanese
    - U.S. Forces Okinawa telephone directory, 1972
  - Business card files (Box 31)
    - News media: Foreign correspondents and Japanese editors and reporters, Okinawan editors, reporters, circa 1960-1970
    - Miscellaneous: government, economic, academic, social, circa 1960-1970
  - Memorabilia: Stone in memory of the dedication of the Samuel C. Oglesby Monument, Okinawa, November 26, 1968
  - Okinawa Files Additional Materials, 1950-2008
    - USCAR notebooks, 1968-1971 (Box-folder 42: 1)
    - Small notebooks, circa 1969 (Box-folder 42: 2)
    - President Eisenhower visit to Okinawa photographs, 19 June 1960 (Box-folder 42: 3)
    - Photographs, 1950-2003 (Box-folder 42: 4-5)
    - U.S. and Japan Okinawa Reversion Agreement, 1971 (Box-folder 42: 6)
    - USCAR in Okinawa collected materials, 1972-2008 (Box-folder 42: 7)
    - Speeches and reference materials, 1972-1992 (Box-folder 43: 1)
    - Correspondence and organizational documents, 1972 (Box-folder 43: 2)
    - Okinawa culture articles and clippings, 1959-2005 (Box-folder 43: 3-4)
    - Okinawa history and geography collected materials, 1964-2004 (Box-folder 43: 5)
    - Battle of Okinawa collected materials, 1945, 1948-2007 (Box-folder 43: 6-7)
    - Commodore Perry and the Gokoku Temple Bell collected materials, 1953-2004 (Box-folder 43: 8)
    - Senkaku Islands collected materials, 2005 (Box-folder 43: 9)
    - Okinawa collected articles, reports, and writings, 2005-2008 (Box-folder 44: 1)
    - The Ryukyuanist newsletter, 2005 (Box-folder 44: 2)
    - News clippings, magazines, and printed materials on Okinawa, 1960-2006 (Box-folder 44: 3-5)
    - U.S. Civil Administration of the Ryukyu Islands book, Dai Nippon Printing Co, Ltd. Tokyo, in Japanese, 1955 (Box-folder 44: 6)
    - "Okinawa: Why Are We There?" Conference, Liosnoff's Speech for Informational Conference on Okinawa, circa 2000 (Box-folder 44: 7)
    - "Okinawa: Why Are We There?" digital image slideshow, 6 CD-Roms, 2005 (Box 47)
    - Okinawa: 50 years of History after World War II video tape, circa 1995 (Box 47)
- Oversize Materials, 1935-2004
  See also Shanghai American School Association Records, Korea Files, and Okinawa Files for additional information
  Contains photograph albums of the Shanghai American School Association, Korea, and Okinawa. Also contains photographs, awards, certificates, maps, and printed matter. Arranged by physical form.
  - Photograph albums
    - Shanghai American School, 1935-1988
    - South Korea, Pusan, and Tokyo, Japan, 1951-1957
    - End of World War II, 1945 to Visit of President Eisenhower to Okinawa, 1960
    - Okinawa, 1953-2004
      Includes groups and individual portraits of visitors and staff as well as recent photographs
  - Oversize photographs (Box 32)
    - U.S. Civil Administrator Robert A. Fearey and U.S. High Commissioner General James B. Lampert, 1972
      Signed portrait photographs
  - Commendation certificates, 1970-1972
  - Printed Matter
    - Daily Pacifican, 1945
    - Maps, Philippines and Tokyo, circa 1944
    - MapTalk, 1944
    - NewsMap, 1943-1945
    - "China's Reconstruction," North China Daily News, 10 October 1936
    - Yank, 1945
    - A New Atlas of China: Land, Air, and Sea Routes, by Marthe Rajchman, John Day Company, New York, 1941 (Box 46)
  - Okinawa Files Additional Materials
    - Certificates of Appreciation from Okinawa, 1962-1963 (Box 46)
    - Okinawan License Plate, 1965 (Box 46)
    - Chieko Liosnoff certificate of appreciation, Okinawa, 1972 (Box 46)
  - Family Identification Documents, 1918-1948 (Box 46)
    - Abram Liosnoff, Chinese Pharmacy certifications in Russian and Chinese, 1934 (Box 46)
    - Abram Liosnoff, American Pharmacy certifications, 1948 (Box 46)
    - Olga Beilin, Jersey City evening school certificate, 1917 (Box 46)
  - Plain English Will transparencies, circa 1980 (Box 46)
- Printed Matter, 1945-1996
  See also Shanghai American School Association Records, Korea Files, and Okinawa files for additional information
  Consists of collected secondary sources mirroring the topics of original documentation in the collection. Of particular note are published works inscribed by authors and Okinawan political figures Masahide Ota and Mikio Higa, personal friends of Liosnoff. Some materials are in Japanese or Chinese. Arranged by subject, and then sorted alphabetically by title.
  - Shanghai American School Association, 1945-1996 (Box 33)
    - 110 Shanghai Road, Monica Highland, McGraw-Hill, New York, 1986
      Inscribed by the authors: Carolyn See, Lisa See, and John Espey
    - Barney: Journals of Harry Virden Bernard, Barbara Bernard McGee and Ruth Dorval Jones, self published, 1982
      Inscribed by the author
    - Bridges to Beginnings, A collection of poems, Agnes Nasmith Johnson, ROAD Publishers, Painter, Virginia, 1996
    - Minor Heresies, John J. Espey, Alfred A. Knopf, New York, 1945
    - Minor Heresies, Major Departures: A China Mission Boyhood, John Espey, University of California Press, 1994
    - Strong Drink, Strong Language, John Espey, John Daniel and Company, Santa Barbara, California, 1990
  - Korea, 1950-1955
    - Four Working Papers on Propaganda Theory, U.S. Information Agency and Institute of Communication Research, University of Illinois, 1955
    - Psychological Warfare, by Paul Myron Anthony Linebarger, Infantry Journal Press, 1950. Inscribed by the author
    - Psychological Warfare, Theories and Application, by Huang Chi-hsing and Chen Ying-leu, translated by Lee Wah-chung, Chi Hsing Press Branch, Hong Kong, 1955, inscribed by the author
  - Okinawa and the Ryukyus, 1955-1996
    - Periodicals and Magazines
      - American Food Fair, 1971
      - Life on Okinawa magazine, 1965
      - Loo-Choo Independent Magazine, 1993
      - Konnichi no Ryukyu (Today's Ryukyus), 1962-1968 (Box 34)
        Incomplete serial, some in Japanese
      - Okinawa International: A monthly publication, August 1958, February 1959, June 1959
      - Okinawa Graph, 1959-1992
        selected issues
      - Operation Goodwill, circa 1971
      - Quarterly Report of the Okinawan Problems, no.2, 1967, no.4, 1969
      - A Request, Ginowan City Hall, May 1998
      - Ryukyu, Executive Government of the Ryukyus, 1955, 1958-1964
      - Shurei No Hikari, (Light of the land of courtesy), 1970-1971
        Incomplete run of periodical includes special reversion issue
      - Shurei No Hikari, (Light of the land of courtesy), 1972 (Box 35)
      - This week on Okinawa, 1959-1966
        Incomplete serial set
      - Welcome Okusan, Officers' Wives Club, 1971
    - Monographs
      - America We Have Seen, the Midori Kai, Okinawa Times, 1955
      - A Brief Glimpse into Okinawa's Past, Shiko Sakumoto, circa 1960s
      - Economic Development Study: Ryukyu Islands, Daniel, Mann Johnson and Medenhall and Japan Economic and Engineering Consultants, Ltd., 1968
      - Expo '75, 1972-1975
      - Expo '75 Bulletin, 1972-1975 (Box 36)
      - Okinawa, Okinawa Prefectural Industries, Promotion Corporation, 1991
      - Okinawa Enno Hokoku (Okinawa Report), Kenjiro Hamanishi, 1961
      - Okinawa History, Bijutsu Shukan design center, 1972
        In Japanese
      - Okinawa Hokoku (Okinawa Report), Asahi Shimbun, 2000
      - Okinawa Information Guide and Telephone Directory, 1964-1971, undated
      - Okinawa Ken 37 years of history: Tenth Anniversary of Reversion, Okinawa Times, Ryukyu Shimpo, George H. Kerr, et al., 1982
      - On the Threshold of the Closed Empire, Edward C. Bollinger, William Carey Library, Pasadena, California, 1991
      - "Political Process of Okinawa Reversion," International Relations, No. 2, 1974
      - Ten Year History of the Ryukyu Development Loan Corporation, 1972 (Box 37)
      - Tours of Okinawa: A Souvenir Guide to Places of Interest, U.S. Army Service Clubs Okinawa, Bridgway Press, 1959
      - Transactions of the Asiatic Society of Japan, v. IV, December 1927
      - True Okinawan Spirit: the Life of Kotaro Kokuba, Kyoh Katoh, undated
        In Japanese, signed by Kotaro Kokuba
      - Researches in Ryukyuan Ancient History, Liang Chia-pin, 1960
      - Reflections on the Okinawan Experience, ed. Ronald Y. Nakasone, Dharma Cloud Publishers, Fremont, California, 1996
      - Ryukyu Development Loan Corporation Annual Report, 1972
      - Sightseeing Okinawa, 1971
      - We Loved Every Minute: Or Life in "Western" Japan, Sanae Yamazaki, Pacific Stars and Stripes, 1958
    - Masahide Ota
      - The Battle of Okinawa, Masahide Ota, 1984
      - A Comparative Study of American and Japanese Cartoons: In relation to the humor involved, Masahide Ota, 1965
      - The Heart of Okinawa, Masahide Ota, 1974
        In Japanese, inscribed by the author
      - Korenga Okinawa Senda (Okinawa War), Masahide Ota, 1977
      - Okinawa Kiyozetsu Suru (Okinawan People's Opinions), Masahide Ota, 1965
      - Okinawa-no Minshu Ishiki (Okinawans' Thinking), Masahide Ota, 1967 (Box 38)
      - Minikui Nihonjin (Ugly Japanese), Masahide Ota, 1970
      - Sensoto Kodomo (War and Children), Masahide Ota, 1980
    - Mikio Higa
      - "The Reversion Theme in Current Okinawan Politics," Mikio Higa, Asian Survey, Institute of International Studies, University of California, v. VII number 3, March 1967
      - Higa Mikio Seishun Den (Mikio Higa's younger days), 1979
        Story with cartoons in Japanese
      - Political and Parties in Postwar Okinawa, Mikio Higa, University of British Columbia, 1963
      - Politics and Parties in Postwar Okinawa, Mikio Higa, published in Japan by Choo-Koron Sha Inc., 1965
  - Japan, 1941, undated
    - Jitsugyo-No-Hawaii, 30th anniversary addition: Featuring timely messages to Japanese people in Hawaii from Army, Navy and civilian leaders, ed. Tetsuo Toyama, 1941
    - Prince Matsuyama Sho Jun's Memorial Works, undated
  - China, 1948-1996
    - China and the World Press, Hollington K. Tong, 1948 (Box 39)
    - China Anthology: Seventy Years of Shanghai Tiffin Perspectives, ed. Victor T.H. Tsuan and Charles C. M. Chung, Compass Books, 1996
    - Chiang Kai-shek, Hollington K. Tong, Dai Nippon Printing Co., Tokyo, 1953
    - Communist China in World Politics, Harold C. Hinton, Houghton Mifflin, Boston, 1966
    - Dateline: China, the Beginnings of China's Press Relations with the World, Hollington K. Tong, Rockport Press, New York, 1950
    - The Rise of Communism in China, 1920-1950, Wang Yah-kang, Chung Shu Publishing Co., Hong Kong, 1951
    - Soviet Russia in China, Chiang Kai-shek, Farrar, Strauss and Cudahy Inc. New York, 1957
      Inscribed by Major General Hsiao Cheng-chih
    - Tentative list of the 1400 most frequently used Chinese characters, undated
- Family Identification Documents, 1915-1946
  - Russian and Chinese passport, 1915, 1916, 1946 (Box-folder 45: 1)
  - Identification documents, Russian, Chinese, and U.S., 1915-1946 (Box-folder 45: 2)
  - Russian portraits, circa 1915-1930 (Box-folder 45: 3)
- Plain Language Materials, 1980-2008
  - Plain English for lawyers, 1981-1985 (Box-folder 45: 4)
  - Language (Plain) forms, 1974-1980 (Box-folder 45: 5)
  - Bank of America Plain Language, 1978-2008 (Box-folder 45: 6-7)
  - Guide to Plain Language, circa 1985 (Box-folder 45: 8)